Chapter 47 The Mataker.
It was a cloudy, sultry afternoon. The seammen were lazily lounging about the
decks or vacantly gazing over into the lead colored waters. Quiquake and I were
mildly employed weaving what is called a sword mat for an additional lashing to
our boat. So still and subdued and somehow proluding was all the scene, and
such an incantation of revery lurked in the air that each silent sailor seemed
resolved into his own invisible self.
I was the attendant or page of Quequ while busy at the mat, as I kept passing
and repassing the filling or woof of Marline between the long yarns of the
warp, using my own hand for the shuttle, and as Quiquake, standing sideways, ever
and an slid his heavy oaken sword between the threads, and idly looking
off upon the water, carelessly and unthinkingly, drove home every yarn. I
say, so strange a dreaminess did there then rain all over the ship and all over
the sea, only broken by the intermittent dull sound of the sword, that it seemed
as if this were the loom of time, and I myself were a shuttle mechanically
weaving and weaving away at the fates.
There lay the fixed threads of the warp, subject to but one single ever returning
unchanging vibration, and that vibration merely enough to admit of the crosswise
interbending of other threads with its own. This warp seemed necessity, and
here thought I, with my own hand, I apply my own shuttle, and weave my own
destiny into these unalterable threads.
Meanwhile, Quequ's impulsive, indifferent sword, sometimes hitting the
wolf slantingly or crookedly or strongly or weakly as the case might be, and by
this difference in the concluding blow, producing a corresponding contrast in
the final aspect of the completed fabric. This savages sword thought I,
which thus finally shapes and fashions both warp and woof. This easy,
indifferent sword must be chance. I, chance, free will and necessity, no wise
incompatible, all interweavingly working together. the straight warp of necessity
not to be swerved from its ultimate course. Its every alternating vibration
indeed only tending to that free will still free to ply her shuttle between
given threads and chance though restrained in its play within the right
lines of necessity and sideways in its motion directed by free will. though
thus prescribed to by both chance by turns rules either and has the last
featuring blow at events.
Thus we were weaving and weaving away when I started at a sound so strange
long drawn and musically wild and unearly that the ball of free will
dropped from my hand and I stood gazing up at the clouds whence that voice had
dropped like a wing. High aloft in the cross trees was that mad gay header
Tashego. His body was reaching eagerly forward, his hands stretched out like a
wand, and at brief sudden intervals he continued his cries. To be sure the same
sound was that very moment perhaps being heard all over the seas, from hundreds
of whaleman's lookouts perched as high in the air. But from few of those lungs
could that accustomed old cry have derived such a marvelous cadence as from
Tashego the Indians. As he stood hovering over you, half suspended in
air, so wildly and eagerly peering towards the horizon, you would have
thought him some prophet or sear beholding the shadows of fate, and by
those wild cries announcing their coming.
There she blows. There, there, there she blows. She blows where away on the lee
beam about 2 mi off a school of them.
Instantly all was commotion. The sperm whale blows as a clock ticks with the
same undeviating and reliable uniformity and thereby whalemen distinguish this
fish from other tribes of his genus.
There go flukes was now the cry from Tashego and the whales disappeared.
Quick, steward, cried Ahab. Time, time.
Doughboy hurried below, glanced at the watch, and reported the exact minute to Ahab.
The ship was now kept away from the wind, and she went gently rolling before
it. Tashego, reporting that the whales had gone down, heading to Lurard, we
confidently looked to see them again directly in advance of our boughs, for
that singular craft at times by the sperm whale, when sounding with his head
in one direction, he nevertheless, while concealed beneath the surface, mills
round and swiftly swims off in the opposite quarter. This deceitfulness of
his could not now be in action, for there was no reason to suppose that the
fish seen by Tashego had been in any way alarmed or indeed knew at all of our
vicinity. One of the men selected for shipkeepers, that is those not appointed
to the boats, by this time relieved the Indian at the main mast head. The
sailors at the for and mizen had come down. The line tubs were fixed in their
places. The cranes were thrust out. The mainard was backed and the three boats
swung over the sea like three samfire baskets over high cliffs. Outside of the
bull works their eager crews with one hand clung to the rail, while one foot
was expectantly poised on the gunnel. So looked the long line of man of wars men
about to throw themselves on board an enemy's ship. But at this critical
instant, a sudden exclamation was heard that took every eye from the whale. With
a start, all glared at dark Ahab, who was surrounded by five dusky phantoms
that seemed fresh formed out of air.